[Music]
[Applause]
in this tutorial we're going to learn to
make socks on 9in circulars using these
little short 9-in circular needles to
fly through the foot and the cuff of the
sock this pattern is sized for women any
shoe size um average shoe width and it
is available for both DK weight and
fingering weight and normally when I put
out a sock pattern I put it in one
weight and then I say you know now that
you have the skills you need you can
move on to all kinds of patterns that
use these techniques but this pattern is
pretty unique in the way that it's
written especially for 9in circulars so
I thought I'd offer it in both weights
if you would like to get your copy of
this pattern to follow along I'll give
you a link here just click the little I
in the upper right hand corner and
you'll see a link there to my website
and on my website you will see all of
the materials you need for either weight
of sock and you'll be able to get your
pattern you'll also see links
information on everything that you see
in the video all the needles that I use
and the Yarns and everything else I'm
going to put this pattern at about um
somewhere between Advanced beginner and
intermediate if you've never knit socks
before this isn't a bad way to start
it's not really that difficult it's um
kind of an pretty easy first sock
pattern but I will encourage you to
practice with 9-in circulars a little
bit they do take I would say at least at
least a few hours um a few inches of
knitting to really start to feel com
comfortable with it where your um your
gauge is really even and it looks really
good anyway these socks are toe up using
German short rows I think everyone who's
tried German short rows um has decided
that it's their favorite way of knitting
socks so I wanted to be sure to include
that and they are knit with an
afterthought heel which makes them you
know you pretty much just knit a tube
and then we'll go back and knit the um
the heel last anyway I think we are
ready to get started we're going to
start with the toe of the sock and I
happen to use a different color of yarn
which is kind of a fun thing um but you
will need double pointed needles to knit
both the toe and the heel we're going to
start with a provisional Caston and
that's coming right
up okay so we're ready to get started
with the tutorial if you'd like to get
your copy of the pattern to follow along
remember you can always click the little
I in the upper right hand corner and
you'll see a link there to my website um
let's go ahead and get started by seeing
the socks close
up these are the DK weight socks and
I've kind of fallen in love with DK
weight socks because they're pretty
quick to knit they wear as nicely as
fingering weight um and also I I like
the yarn choices that I have you'll see
here that um you'll see here that I've
knit the toe and the heel in a different
color it's totally not necessary I just
thought it was
cute um so that's DK weight and then we
have the fingering weight here they're
kind of lumpy and wrinkly because they
haven't shoved in a bag I also haven't
blocked them yet but um much smaller
stitches these take a while longer to
knit but they're a finer Fabric and nice
to
wear and we are going to start with a
provisional Caston toe and for this
we're going to want to use double
pointed
needles and um I am going to use much
bulkier yarn and much thicker needles to
do this um as I usually do in my
tutorials so you can see what I'm more
easily see what I'm doing I'm using
bulky yarn and uh I think size 10
needles and we are going to um do a
crochet chain right onto the knitting
needle to get started the first thing I
want to do is I want to take a color of
yarn that is not the color I'm using for
the toe of the sock I'm going to tie a
knot in the
yarn and then I'm going to make a slip
knot
and I'll take my crochet hook and just
chain a few stitches
now I released a video recently a short
technique video showing how to do this
so this is a way of doing a provisional
Caston a crochet provisional Caston
without having to pick up stitches from
the spine of the crochet chain so I have
my crochet hook in my dominant hand I'm
going to uh put the knitting needle over
the working yarn like this and then
reach over the needle grab the yarn and
pull it through and you've just cast on
one stitch pull the yarn back
pull the yarn
back and I always find my tensions a
little bit looser than it would be if I
picked up the stitches but since I'll be
ripping this out and throwing this yarn
away it's it's just waste yarn it
doesn't
matter and the next row of knitting
turns out to be fine the tension's
fine and I'm just going to do an
abbreviated sample here you will of
course follow the directions and the
pattern for the number that you are
casting
on um no I think I'll actually stop
there okay and
then whoops I am losing stitches I
wanted to have 12 for this
example then just chain a few another
few more
stitches and you can break this
yarn I'm sorry I didn't my have my
scissors
out I don't seem to have any
scissors okay and then just pull the
last loop I see the scissors now pull
the last Loop through there and don't
tighten it too much because we're going
to undo this pretty
soon and then using the yarn that you
actually want to use for the toe of the
sock we are going to start at the slip
knot end and remember you tied a knot in
the
yarn and just knit across these stitches
you take your working yarn fold it over
and wrap the back needle and pull it
through and we've attached a new yarn
and you can just knit
across now this first row that we're
knitting actually Catches Us up to where
we would be in the pattern if we picked
up stitches from the crochet chain does
that make
sense when once I finish this row
there's no difference in what I've done
here or picking up stitches from the
crochet
chain and then we're going to Pearl back
across these stitches before we get
started on the German short rows
okay now if you've worked the German
short row technique in uh my sock
patterns before this is no different I'm
going to show you how to do it on just a
few right side and wrong side
rows um of course the instructions are
written out rowby row and the technique
is written out in really clear
instructions in the pattern I am just
going to demonstrate the techniques here
so you can see how it's
done and the first thing I did was I
knit across all the stitches to the last
Stitch I'm going to do a German short
row technique on this last Stitch so I
turn the
work slip that Stitch from the left
needle to the right and this is the way
you work the German short R technique
when the wrong side of the work is
facing
you then pull up on that Stitch so you
get kind of a funny double Stitch pull
the yarn forward between the two needles
to Pearl
across you're going to Pearl up to the
last Stitch and we're going to work the
German short row technique on this side
so turn the work and this is the way
you're going to work it when the right
side of the work is facing you slip that
Stitch from the left needle to the
right take your working yarn and pull up
and you'll get a funny double Stitch but
it'll look different than the funny
double Stitch that we did on the other
side and keep your working yarn in back
and knit across to the second to last
Stitch
okay now we're going to do a short row T
turn on this so I knit it I turn the
work slip that Stitch from the left
needle to the right pull up on the
working yarn to get the funny double
Stitch and pull the yarn forward between
the two needles so that we can Pearl
okay I knit up to the second to last
Stitch turn the work pull the yarn
forward between the two needles slip
that Stitch from the left needle to the
right pull up on the working
yarn and then knit to the third the last
Stitch I'm just going to show you this
one more time before we start working
the second half of the toe one more time
on each
side turn the
work slip the
Stitch pull up pull the yarn forward to
Pearl turn the
work okay actually I'm done working the
first half of the toe here or my
abbreviated bulky version of it if you
take a look we definitely have some
shaping going on the work is narrower on
the two sides and uh longer in the
middle wider in the
middle so now I've knit up um to the
first funny double Stitch I'm going to
knit the two halves of the funny double
stitch together and the next one and
turn the work and we're going to work a
normal German short row technique here
slip the Stitch pull up on it everything
looks a little bit different because the
Stitch Below had a a German short row
turn on it and pearl across
oops and then when we get to the first
funny double Stitch I'm going to Pearl
those two together and the next Stitch
the next Double Stitch turn the
work slip that Stitch pull up on it and
knit
across it's funny for a tutorial on
socks on 9in circulars the longest part
of this video is going to be on double
pointed needles the most complicated
shaped
part now the first double Stitch is is
two from the
end and I'm going to knit those two
together the two Hales of the funny
double Stitch and the next
one I want to make it all the way
through this abbreviated toe so I can
show you how to remove the provisional
Caston and switch to the 9in circulars
okay now I'm going to knit up to the
last double stitch on the right side
and it's the last one I'm going to knit
those two together there's no further to
go so I'm just going to turn the
work slip that
Stitch and pearl
across and again this is all written out
out row by Row in the
pattern and the last double pearl stitch
just Pearl
together okay here we
are with our little abbreviated bulky
German short row toe it looks like it
looks like the toe of a sock not ideal
but it I mean
it is just a chunk a chunky sample of a
sock for
sure and what we're going to do now is
take out the provisional Caston um and
start putting these stitches onto the
9in circular needles so if you put the
work in front of you with the cast on
facing you you should have the slip knot
side over here on the left and the
non-slip knot side over here on the
right and I get a lot of emails from
people who who panic and they say oh
it's on I don't have the same as you
mine are switched around just work a row
on this needle to get yourself in the
right position there's it won't make a
difference in the the final um in the
final sock so we just ended this by
pulling the the the yarn through the
last Loop I'm going
to tease that back out and start to
unravel to rip out the unzip the
provisional cast on and if you've done
um uh provisional cast on before the
first Stitch is always wonky the yarn
actually runs through
it so I'll put my needle in there I'm
using the circular needles now and get
that yarn out of the
Stitch okay from here on out it's
easier when you're looking at this
follow the v's up and you'll see that
there is the the top V and it's
connected to the scrap yarn that we used
you want to pick up the right leg you to
go behind the right leg of the top V in
the in the sock yarn that we're
using so there's my first
one second
one and I like to pick up a whole bunch
of
ones and then once you get them on the
needle you can pull on the crochet chain
and you'll see because we did the
crochet chain this way nothing snags
because we didn't split any
stitches and you can do that when you're
picking up stitches from the spine of
the croch crochet
chain
okay now I have half of my let me get
this yarn out of the way I have half of
my stitches on the 9-in circular and
half of them on the double pointed
needle this is a good time to tie the
working yarn to the tail it keeps there
from being a gap there and now we're
going to um actually I don't have a
marker out I want to place a marker
here uh a little round stitch marker I
can quickly get one
here I don't want to forget to do that
okay I'm going to put a marker there so
I know where the beginning of my round
is and knit
across from the double pointed needle to
the 9in circulars
okay you are done with double pointed
needles for a while and you'll want to
follow the pattern but if you want to
change colors you can do that um you'll
want to do at the beginning of the round
knit up to the next
marker the 9 in circulars that I'm using
here are of course much bigger than the
9in circulars that you'll use for the
actual socks this is for the DK weight
um as much as I H am enjoying using 9-in
circulars I will tell you they get more
difficult to use with chunkier yarn in
bigger needle sizes but I want to use um
chunkier yarn and bigger needles for the
demonstration okay everything's ready
for you to start flying around on these
circulars
and of course you'll want to reference
the pattern to tell you exactly when to
change color how long to make the foot
and um when to start the heel and that's
what we're going to cover next is
setting the
heel you followed the pattern around and
around on the 9in circulars to get the
sock as long as you need it for your
shoe size and the pattern tells you
exactly how far that is and references
the different shoe sizes and the number
of inches that you need of length and
you'll get to a part where we want to
set the heel and we're really just going
to um kind of Mark the heel with a line
of stitches that we can remove later and
then the last thing we'll do is to go
back and knit the heel kind of add it to
the finished sock um and then a couple
other things but let's go ahead and get
started with setting the
heel here is the chunky example I've
knit the sock as long as I need it for
my shoe size and I'm ready to set the
heel here in the work I say set the heel
I don't um I couldn't think of another
word for it um what I want to do is to
take another color of yarn that is not
my sock yarn color and I'm also going to
take a double pointed needle I found it
was easier to do this with a different
needle I'm going to knit across the
number of stitches indicated in the
pattern
for the weight of sock that I'm
knitting we're ignoring the working yarn
and just using this scrap yarn to knit
across okay I knit across those
stitches now I found my scissors break
that yarn and I want to slip these
stitches back onto the circular and
because I'm right-handed I like to do it
from from this side I like to slip two
stitches in my right hand so I only
needed the double pointed needle for
quick minute
there I'll take care of that in a minute
just slip
these okay there's something that I
neglected to do I want the scrap yarn to
hang down here in
front both sides there we
go and now I'm just going to knit across
those stitches
like nothing I didn't do anything
different and you'll be able to
tell these chunk key 9in circulars are
not the easiest thing to work with it's
a lot easier on the smaller size like I
said before um you'll be able to tell
where your line of heel stitches are
because you'll have the two ends hanging
in front and this different color there
now you'll um set the heel and then go
on to knit the cuff for um you can knit
the cuff for as long as you can I
usually leave about five gram of yarn to
work the sock cuff and to have enough
for the bind off I that's one of the
great things about toe up socks is that
you can use all your yarn so I always
like to use it all up um and you'll work
the ribbing and then I want to show you
how to work this bind off because it's
kind of a modification to the super
stretchy bindoff that I am using for
socks all the time now I guess I've
known about this technique for about a
year I love it and we have one by one
rib going here so I'm going to knit the
first Stitch then Pearl the next Stitch
Stitch and then I'm going to put my
needle into the back of those two my
left needle into the back of those two
stitches I just worked wrap the needle
and pull it through and then knit the
next Stitch and because the last Stitch
was a knit I'm going to put my needle
into the front of those two stitches
wrap the back needle and pull it through
so this is what the pattern looks like
I'm going to knit the knits and pearl
the pearls and if the Stitch I just knit
was a knit I'm going to knit the two
stitches together and if the Stitch I
just worked was a pearl I'm going to
Pearl the two stitches together and this
is what makes a really stretchy bind off
that looks really good too so I'm going
to yarn forward in
Pearl and then put the needle into the
back of those two stitches wrap the
needle and pull it
through
knit Put the Needle into the front of
those two stitches
Pearl
back
knit
front you see here you end up with a
nice looking um bind off that has a lot
of give to it it's going to fit nicely
around the calf um especially if you're
using all of your yarn and the sock's
going to have to be stretchy enough to
fit up higher on the calf you want to
make sure you have a good stretchy bind
off now when you're finished with the
bindoff I'm going to pull in another
example here we're going to use this
example in the next
section um when you're finished with the
bindoff you will have kind of a stair
Steppy jog you see that where the last
Stitch and the first Stitch don't really
match up and that's because knitting in
the round is essentially knitting in a
spiral so I'm going to show you how to
weave in the end to fix that up you take
your tapestry needle
and the end of the
yarn and
put put the needle through both legs of
the V of the first Stitch that you see
here and then put it down back into the
same hole you came out
of and look at that well I can
straighten it out a little better than
that that looks really good if it didn't
look quite right I'd pull it out and try
again but then you can just weave in the
ends from here and you are done with the
cuff of the
sock and that by that um little
technique you can use anytime you're
trying to tidy up uh bindoff stitches in
the round like
that okay next up we're going to work
the heel and graph the heel together in
a few last little bits
okay we are finished with the sock and
we're ready to go back and put a heel in
it you could at this point I suppose
leave it a tube sock but we are going to
put a heel in these socks I'm going to
show you how to do it just in case let's
go and take a
look here is where we left the sock last
time I'm going to go ahead and pull
these needles out and I Don't Panic it's
okay I just don't want them flopping
around while we're working on the actual
heel
stitches so the best way to do this is
to take needles that are smaller than
the needles that you used in the sock
it's just easier that way and we're
going to take out this row of stitches
and this really isn't that hard but I
know it makes people panic when there
are live stitches hanging around with um
with no one retrieving them saving them
but so sit yourself in a place where you
have good light and where you have a
time when you have a few minutes to take
care of this where you don't have to
leave it in the middle and come back to
it because it is a good idea to get
stitches picked up quickly if you
leaving them live so we see this first V
here the first V is different as they
always are and the yarn actually starts
with the left leg of this
V excuse
me so start that and pull that out and
then pull out the right leg of the V and
then from here on out it's going to go
right left right left
and I always like to keep this yarn um
pretty short it's so I'm not pulling
through a bunch of waist yarn
okay this is the part where people
really start to panic but I swear
there's nothing to worry about it's fine
you have your smaller needle um you you
want to pick these stitches up and to
get them mounted correctly on the needle
we want to pick them up from the back to
the front all the way across
and of course this looks really easy CU
I'm using such chunky yarn but this
really isn't hard even in a small gauge
it's surprisingly more
easy surprising more is easier than you
think it would
be so I have all the bottom
stitches and I'm going to turn this the
other way because I like to work across
from the right to the left
and when you're finished you will
have you'll have all of the um stitches
on the toe side on one needle and the
stitches on the cuff side on two needles
and you'll have one more stitch on the
bottom needle there's one stitch fewer
up here on these and that's totally
normal that's the way it's supposed to
be now you're going to follow your
pattern because um and start knitting
across these stitches and working the
short row heel and the crazy thing is
and you know this already if you've knit
German Short Road socks before the heel
and the toe are worked exactly the same
so the pattern spells it out row by row
but you're going to knit across all
these stitches and work the whole toe
where you're starting the German short
rows and then picking them back up you
know knitting through the double
stitches and then when you're finished
you'll end up with something that looks
like this oh I kind of forgot to tell
you we've picked everything up on these
smaller needles but you actually want to
switch over to the larger needles when
you start working um start working these
stitches to work the heel the smaller
needles were just for picking them
up so this is what we have here now the
toe or the heel it's it looks just like
the toe the heel is finished I have um
let cut the yarn the working yarn
leaving a bit of a tail because I'm
going to Kitchener Stitch these um
stitches together and I'll show you how
that
looks I need a tapestry needle for
this Kitchener Stitch is a way of
grafting the stitches together without
leaving any Ridge or
anything I'm going to transfer these to
one
needle make it easier to see what I'm
doing if no one was watching me I
wouldn't transfer it to one needle but
make it easier
so my working yarn is here I line up the
stitches on the front and the back
needle and now I'm going to graph these
together I have a couple of setup
stitches here I'm going to go through
the stitch on the front needle as if to
Pearl and go through the stitch on the
back needle as if to knit those are my
little setup
stitches now to go through the the steps
of Kitchener Stitch it's goes front
needle front needle back needle back
needle so knit
off
Pearl Pearl off knit and you give it a
good
tug we start over knit off
Pearl Pearl off knit and then give it a
good
tug and this is truly the little chant
that I say while I'm doing kitchen or
Stitch
okay I'm not going to go all the way
across but you will definitely want to
follow the pattern because there in a
little accommodation made at the end of
this process um because there's one
stitch fewer on the top needle than the
bottom I'm just going to pull that out
and when you work across you can really
tighten this up you can see you can
scrunch it up and then smooth it out
that's usually what I do to make sure
that it's all even and smooth now the
last thing I want to address here is
that you will have this worked all the
way across I only need part of it done
so I can show you this you will have a
significant Gap here and we are going to
use the tail end the end that we Ed to
start knitting the heel to close this up
and there are a couple of ways that you
can do it I tried out a couple of
different ways and I was happy with both
of them but I'll um I'll show you you
can if you like using the mattress
stitch you can mattress stitch these two
sides together by going by picking up
the ladders between two stitches over
here and picking up the ladders between
two stitches over here and just going
back and forth I found that I like to do
kind of a bicycle
spoke um design instead and so instead
of just closing it up it kind of makes
it decorative and I'm not sure I'm going
to have the greatest results with this
bulky yarn but we'll give it a try I'm
going to go into the center of the heel
stitches here to get myself
started and
then I'm going to just go between
stitches and back down into the same
place this is I think we're going to
have a tough time with this bulky yarn
making it look really good but I
definitely want to show you the
technique and then a little bit of space
and go between two stitches and back
down to the same
spot tighten this up and then again
actually this is not looking the way I
want it to
look let me try this one more
time okay there's my starting
spot it's really actually pretty easy
with the lighter weight yarn
and it makes a bicycle spoke
design oh that's looking
better not quite you get the idea I hope
I'm going to show you on the finished
socks excuse me what it looks like um
just because the yarn is big and bulky
we have a gap there but you see kind of
it makes this decorative design
decorative design makes this decorative
pattern here let
me grab
a here we
go here's the little bicycle spoke
design on this side me see I was kind of
inventing the technique and working on
the sock at the same time you see that
looks nice and there's absolutely no Gap
there and in the DK weight
version see how cute that looks it looks
like a little
flower and and that will be the last
step that you have to do to finish up
your
socks once the Gap is closed up and well
the sock was bound off a while ago once
the Kitchener Stitch is worked and the
gaps are closed up you are finished and
ready to move on to the next pair anyway
I hope you enjoy this tutorial I can't
wait to see the colors and Yarns that
you guys use I always check rivalry to
see the projects you post them there I
will definitely see them good luck
[Music]
n